who introduced me to the effects of combat on the psyche. While my grandfather was serving as a Marine in the Korean War, a bullet pierced his neck and rendered him unable to cry out. He watched as a corpsman passed him over, declaring him a goner, and then leaving him to die. Years later, after his physical wounds had healed and he'd returned home, he rarely spoke of his experiences in waking life. But at night I would hear him shouting obscenities from his room down the hall. And during the day I would announce myself as I entered the room, careful not to startle or agitate him. He lived out the remainder of his days isolated and tight-lipped, never finding a way to express himself, and I didn't yet have the tools to guide him. I wouldn't have a name for my grandfather's condition until I was in my 20s. Seeking a graduate degree in art therapy, I naturally gravitated towards the study of trauma. And while sitting in class learning about post-traumatic stress disorder, or PTSD for short, my mission to help service members who suffered like my grandfather began to take form. We've had various names for post-traumatic stress throughout the history of war: homesickness, soldier's heart, shell shock, thousand-yard stare, for instance. And while I was pursuing my degree, a new war was raging, and thanks to modern body armor and military vehicles, service members were surviving blast injuries they wouldn't have before. But the invisible wounds were reaching new levels, and this pushed military doctors and researchers to try and truly understand the effects that traumatic brain injury, or TBI, and PTSD have on the brain. Due to advances in technology and neuroimaging, we now know there's an actual shutdown in the Broca's, or the speech-language area of the brain, after an individual experiences trauma. This physiological change, or speechless terror as it's often called, coupled with mental health stigma, the fear of being judged or misunderstood, possibly even removed from their current duties, has led to the invisible struggles of our servicemen and women. Generation after generation of veterans have chosen not to talk about their experiences, and suffer in solitude. I had my work cut out for me when I got my first job as an art therapist at the nation's largest military medical center, Walter Reed. After working for a few years on a locked-in patient psychiatric unit, I eventually transferred to the National Intrepid Center of Excellence, NICoE, which leads TBI care for active duty service members. Now, I believed in art therapy, but I was going to have to convince service members,
quien me hizo conocer los efectos de la guerra en la psique. Cuando mi abuelo fue Infante de la Marina en la Guerra de Corea, una bala le perforó el cuello, dejándolo sin poder gritar. Vio cómo un médico del ejército siguió de largo, dándolo por desahuciado, y dejándolo ahí para morir. Años después, cuando sus heridas físicas habían sanado y había regresado a casa, rara vez hablaba durante el día de sus experiencias. Pero, durante la noche, lo oía gritar obscenidades al otro lado del pasillo. Al entrar a su cuarto de día, siempre anunciaba mi llegada para no sobresaltarlo o agitarlo. Vivió el resto de sus días aislado y reservado, nunca encontrando la manera de poderse expresar, y yo, en ese entonces, no tenía las herramientas para ayudarlo. No supe el nombre de la condición de mi abuelo hasta alcanzar mis veinte años. Al querer graduarme en Arteterapia, naturalmente me incliné por el estudio del trauma. Y, al aprender en clase sobre el trastorno por estrés postraumático, o TEPT, mi misión de ayudar a militares que han sufrido como mi abuelo comenzó a tomar forma. Le hemos dado diversos nombres al estrés postraumático desde el inicio de las guerras: añoranza, corazón de soldado, aturdimiento, mirada de los mil metros, entre otros. Y mientras estudiaba, una nueva guerra se intensificaba, y, gracias a los modernos chalecos antibalas y vehículos militares, los soldados ahora sobrevivían a explosiones. Pero, las heridas invisibles alcanzaban nuevos niveles, y esto llevó a que médicos e investigadores militares trataran de entender realmente los efectos de una lesión cerebral traumática o TBI, y del trastorno por estrés postraumático en el cerebro. Gracias a los avances en tecnología y a las neuroimágenes, ahora sabemos que ocurre un bloqueo en el área de Broca; esto es, el área del lenguaje del cerebro, cuando un individuo sufre un trauma. Este cambio fisiológico, o "terror sin habla", como también se le conoce, unido al estigma de cordura, el temor a ser juzgados o incomprendidos, tal vez hasta apartados de sus tareas actuales, conduce a las batallas invisibles de nuestros militares, hombres y mujeres. Generaciones de veteranos han preferido no hablar de sus experiencias, y sufren en solitario. Tuve un gran reto al tener mi primer trabajo como arteterapeuta en el mayor centro médico militar del país, Walter Reed. Tras trabajar un par de años en la unidad de pacientes internados, me transfirieron al Centro Intrépido Nacional de Excelencia, NICoE, que lidera el cuidado de TBI para militares en activo. Yo creía en la arteterapia, pero tenía que convencer a los militares,
big, tough, strong, manly military men, and some women too, to give art-making as a psychotherapeutic intervention a try. The results have been nothing short of spectacular.
grandes, rudos, fuertes, masculinos, y a algunas mujeres también, de que ofrecieran hacer arte como tratamiento psicoterapéutico. Los resultados han sido espectaculares.
Vivid, symbolic artwork is being created by our servicemen and women, and every work of art tells a story. We've observed that the process of art therapy bypasses the speech-language issue with the brain. Art-making accesses the same sensory areas of the brain that encode trauma. Service members can use the art-making to work through their experiences in a nonthreatening way. They can then apply words to their physical creations, reintegrating the left and the right hemispheres of the brain. Now, we've seen this can work with all forms of art -- drawing, painting, collage -- but what seems to have the most impact is mask-making. Finally, these invisible wounds don't just have a name, they have a face. And when service members create these masks, it allows them to come to grips, literally, with their trauma. And it's amazing how often that enables them
Nuestros militares, hombres y mujeres están creando obras de arte vívidas y simbólicas, y cada obra cuenta una historia. Hemos observado que el proceso del arteterapia esquiva el problema habla-lenguaje en el cerebro. Hacer arte accede a las áreas sensoriales del cerebro que codifican el trauma. Los militares pueden aprovechar el arte para trabajar sus experiencias de una manera no amenazante. Pueden posteriormente nombrar o describir sus obras, reintegrando los hemisferios izquierdo y derecho del cerebro. Hemos observado que esto funciona con cualquier tipo de arte -- dibujo, pintura, collage -- pero lo que parece tener el mayor impacto es hacer máscaras. Al fin y al cabo, estas heridas invisibles no sólo tienen un nombre, tienen también una cara. Y cuando los militares crean estas máscaras, literalmente tocan y lidian con el trauma. Y es impresionante cómo eso les permite
to break through the trauma and start to heal. Remember BFIB? That was a real experience for one of my patients, and when he created his mask, he was able to let go of that haunting image. Initially, it was a daunting process for the service member, but eventually he began to think of BFIB as the mask, not his internal wound, and he would go to leave each session, he would hand me the mask, and say, "Melissa, take care of him." Eventually, we placed BFIB in a box to further contain him, and when the service member went to leave the NICoE, he chose to leave BFIB behind. A year later, he had only seen BFIB twice, and both times BFIB was smiling and the service member didn't feel anxious.
fracturar el trauma y comenzar a sanar. Recuerdan la CSB? Eso fue una experiencia real para uno de mis pacientes, y cuando creó su máscara, pudo superar esa imagen que lo atormentaba. Al principio, fue un proceso abrumador para el paciente, pero, poco a poco, comenzó a identificar la CSB como máscara y no como su herida interna, y cada vez que terminábamos una sesión, me entregaba la máscara y me decía, "Melissa, cuídalo". Después de un tiempo, metimos a la CSB en una caja, para contenerla y dominarla, y cuando el paciente dejó el NICoE, decidió dejar la CSB. Un año después, había visto a la CSB sólo dos veces, y, en ambas ocasiones la CSB sonreía y el paciente no sintió angustia.
Now, whenever that service member is haunted by some traumatic memory, he continues to paint.
Ahora, cada vez que es atormentado por algún recuerdo traumático, sigue pintando.
Every time he paints these disturbing images, he sees them less or not at all.
Y cada vez que pinta estas imágenes perturbadoras, las ve con menos frecuencia o deja de verlas por completo.
Philosophers have told us for thousands of years that the power to create
Los filósofos nos han dicho desde hace miles de años que el poder de crear
is very closely linked to the power to destroy. Now science is showing us that the part of the brain that registers a traumatic wound can be the part of the brain where healing happens too. And art therapy is showing us how to make that connection. We asked one of our service members to describe how mask-making impacted his treatment, and this is what he had to say. (Video) Service Member: You sort of just zone out into the mask. You zone out into the drawing, and for me, it just released the block, so I was able to do it. And then when I looked at it after two days, I was like, "Holy crap, here's the picture, here's the key, here's the puzzle," and then from there it just soared. I mean, from there my treatment just when out of sight, because they were like, Kurt, explain this, explain this. And for the first time in 23 years, I could actually talk about stuff openly to, like, anybody. I could talk to you about it right now if I wanted to, because it unlocked it. It's just amazing. And it allowed me to put 23 years of PTSD and TBI stuff together in one place that has never happened before. Sorry. Melissa Walker: Over the past five years, we've had over 1,000 masks made. It's pretty amazing, isn't it? Thank you. (Applause) I wish I could have shared this process with my grandfather, but I know that he would be thrilled that we are finding ways to help today's and tomorrow's service members heal, and finding the resources within them that they can call upon to heal themselves. Thank you. (Applause)
está íntimamente relacionado con el poder de destrucción. Ahora la ciencia nos muestra que el área del cerebro que registra una lesión traumática puede ser la misma parte del cerebro donde ocurre la sanación. Y, el arteterapia nos enseña cómo hacer esa conexión. Le pedimos a uno de nuestros pacientes que describiera cómo el hacer máscaras ha impactado en su tratamiento, y esto fue lo que dijo. (Video) Paciente: Simplemente te pierdes en la máscara. Te pierdes en el dibujo, y me desbloqueó, y por eso pude hacerlo. Y, cuando la vi después de dos días, dije "Dios mío, ésta es la pintura, ésta es la llave, éste es el acertijo," y, a partir de ahí, mi tratamiento se disparó es decir, se desahogó, porque me decían, Kurt, explica esto, explica esto. Y, por primera vez en 23 años, pude realmente hablar abiertamente con cualquiera. Podría hablarles de ello ahora si quisiera, porque lo liberé. Es impresionante. Y me permitió colocar 23 años de TEPT y de TBI en un solo lugar. Eso nunca me había pasado. Lo siento. Melissa Walker: En los últimos 5 años se han hecho más de mil máscaras. Es increíble, no? Gracias. (Aplausos) Me hubiera encantado compartir este proceso con mi abuelo, pero sé que estaría emocionado de que estamos encontrando maneras para ayudar a sanar a los militares de hoy y mañana, y dándoles herramientas internas que pueden utilizar para sanarse a sí mismos. Gracias. (Aplausos)